Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Lordship.
Did Ajin upset you yesterday?
No, Ajin has always been plain-spoken.
Regardless of what he said,
I wouldn't be angry.
Your marriage is happy news.
I knew you would say that.
Duke of State Pei has a prominent family.
Although he doesn't have real power,
he is a cultured man.
The daughter he raised must be poised and gracious.
Besides, the Empress Dowager also favors her.
Jingxian...
Her name sounds kind and decorous.
I congratulate Your Lordship.
Do you really mean it?
Of course.
Allow me to help you.
Whether you truly mean it or not,
I only want you to know...
I have no interest in Meng Jingxian.
No matter how good she is,
she is not the person I care for.
But the Empress Dowager is very fond of Miss Meng.
And Your Lordship has reached
a marriageable age.
Her Majesty doesn't know,
but you do.
Even if Your Lordship doesn't like Miss Meng,
Her Majesty will select another suitable lady for you.
Will Your Lordship be able to reject them all?
Also, the person Your Lordship is fond of
might not feel the same for you.
I'm not His Majesty.
My marriage won't have any effect on the state's future.
Her Majesty won't force me either.
As to whether or not the person I like
feels the same about me,
I only believe that...
"with dedicated effort,
even a rock will break open."
With dedicated effort, perhaps the rock
will break open one day.
But my heart is like still water
that doesn't want to ripple again.
It is inappropriate for men to frequent
the Temple of Pure Dew.
And I don't want to be the subject of gossip.
Your Lordship, we should meet
only when necessary.
Did I offend you?
No, you didn't.
But we're as far apart as clouds and mud.
Your Lordship is a descendent of the imperial family.
You shouldn't come here so often.
You don't want to see me?
I don't, because we shouldn't be seeing each other.
I hope Your Lordship will respect my wishes.
If you wish...
so be it.
Ever since winter arrived,
Mistress, you have been coughing nonstop.
You can't sleep well at night
and are having night sweats.
What can we do?
How was it?
I went to Dr. Wen's residence,
but they said the Empress Dowager has been ill
since the beginning of winter.
Dr. Wen stays in the palace to care for
Her Majesty
and is not allowed to leave.
Her Majesty's health takes priority.
It is only reasonable that Dr. Wen
puts forth his best effort.
Only when Her Majesty is well,
will she have Madam Orchid come to look after us.
The snow pear simmered with
rock sugar hasn't helped at all.
Fortunately, His Lordship sent Ajin
to bring you some bird's nest.
It is best for nourishing the lungs.
Mistress,
how about having this now?
I'll finish copying before I eat.
I'm not that fragile.
It's only a couple of coughs.
It's not just a couple of coughs.
You are wracked by coughing.
Even so, Jingbai still ordered My Lady
to wash all the clothes by the stream.
You must have exhausted yourself from all the work.
Jade, please refrain yourself.
Mistress's cough has already stirred up
a lot of rumors.
Some even harshly accused her
of catching tuberculosis.
Who said such nonsense?
It's their ill treatment that has
worsened My Lady's health!
We can't have someone with tuberculosis
living in the Temple of Pure Dew.
- That's right.
- Who would dare come offer incense now?
The ancient temple's reputation
must not be ruined by a person of ill omen.
Who said My Lady caught tuberculosis?
Which doctor confirmed it?
Spreading such nonsense...
Aren't you afraid of being struck by lightning?
You...
Even if it's not tuberculosis,
it's not far from it.
- Right.
- Yes, that's right.
She is coughing day and night.
How can we live here with her?
- Indeed.
- Who would want to live here?
Even looking at her brings bad luck.
It's my fault.
My ill health has been a burden to everyone.
If you know you are a burden,
you should leave immediately.
You're becoming a nuisance by refusing to leave.
- Exactly.
- True, true.
Look!
She's a thief!
The spoils are right here.
What?
You can't make groundless accusations.
When did I ever steal from you?
Only Madam Abbess and I consume
bird's nest in the temple.
Where did you get the bird's nest?
- Exactly.
- Where did you get it from?
That doctor hasn't come to visit you in a while.
Don't tell me he was the one
who gave you the bird's nest.
The Madam from the palace hasn't
visited in months either.
If you didn't steal from me or Madam Abbess,
did the bird's nest just grow out of your bowl?
- Exactly.
- Where did this come from?
She reports to Prioress Jingbai every day
after she is done collecting firewood.
She must have stolen it then.
- I agree.
- It must be her.
Since you eat bird's nest often -
if it was stolen,
you would have noticed it earlier.
Why would you wait until now
to bring this up?
I don't have time to waste my breath on you.
If you can,
simply explain where you obtained the bird's nest.
If you can't,
then you must have stolen it from me.
- Exactly!
- She's right!
You can have the bird's nest,
why can't others have it, too?
Others?
Others may have family who will send them things.
But Mochou was expelled from the palace.
How could she have such valuable bird's nest?
Exactly.
A thief is a thief.
You can't deny it.
I'll go get Madam Abbess.
What happened? What happened?
What's with all the commotion?
Mochou is a thief,
who stole my bird's nest.
She also has tuberculosis.
so she can't live here anymore.
Indeed.
That's enough.
I have been aware for quite a while of
the torture you all inflicted upon her.
You really can't tolerate her?
It's not that we can't tolerate her.
But she was expelled from the palace.
I'm sure you know the sentiments
of those in the palace.
If we continue to allow her to live here,
sooner or later,
she will bring trouble to the temple.
- It's true.
- Yes.
That's enough.
Mochou is rather pitiful.
Madam Abbess, if you show
compassion for Mochou now,
we will be the pitiful ones later.
- She's right.
- Exactly.
How did you become so sick?
Then...
then what about the claim of tuberculosis?
No doctor has seen me and
confirmed it's tuberculosis.
I just have a severe cough.
Have you been taking medicine?
Yes, she has.
But it hasn't taken effect yet.
Mochou has been coughing like this
for more than half a month.
She actually started coughing two months ago,
but it wasn't as severe.
If it's not tuberculosis,
why hasn't the medicine shown effects yet?
- Exactly.
- That's right.
Look how skinny she is.
Her face flushes when coughing.
She probably has deadly tuberculosis.
We can't live with her any longer.
- Right.
- We surely can't.
Mochou,
Since you are in ill health,
and they're not willing to live with you.
What about... moving out for now?
Madam Abbess...
You know...
that we have no one to depend on.
Where can we move to?
As Abbess, you should administer justice,
but have been swayed by a
group of nuns shouting nonsense.
How spineless you are!
Shut your mouth!
How dare you criticize the abbess!
You can reply with words.
Why do you have to hit her?
Madam Abbess,
Can I offer an opinion?
We don't know if our mistress has tuberculosis yet.
But she is very sick and fragile now.
And it's frozen and snowy outside.
Where can we move to
on the spur of the moment?
Madam Abbess, I'm begging you,
please give us a few days' grace.
How can she live with us while being so sick?
Exactly.
How can we sleep when she coughs day and night?
Yes, and she is a thief!
She stole the bird's nest today,
who knows what she will steal tomorrow?
We will not live here if Mochou stays any longer.
- Right! We won't live here.
- Exactly. We won't.
Since the Temple of Pure Dew can't tolerate us,
I won't create a dilemma for Madame Abbess.
However,
I'm not a thief.
I didn't steal the bird's nest.
Since there is no place for us here,
let's leave.
I...
Go pack up our things.
Madam Abbess...
You are thieves.
So we have to check the things you're taking with you.
- You...
- If you smuggle something out of here,
ownership will be your word against ours.
Jingbai,
stop!
This place...
holds no worth for you.
I'll help you to pack up things
and walk you out afterwards.
Mochou,
there are some living quarters on Peak Lingyun,
You can stay there for now and take a rest from practicing.
Let's wait until you return to health.
Thank you, Madam Abbess.
Look at her feigning.
Anyone who wants to complain can
talk to me directly!
My Lady!
- Mistress!
- My Lady!
She's burning up!
What should we do?
With such a heavy snow,
we can't make it to Peak Lingyun anytime soon.
And we can't go back to the Temple of Pure Dew.
We're stranded in this deserted place,
where no doctor can be found.
What should we do?
Where are we now?
It's not completely deserted.
Jade,
the Cooling Terrace is ahead!
There is only one person we can ask for help.
Go quickly!
My Lady!
What should we do...
What is taking Jade so long?
Will the person you mentioned come?
I am not sure.
We have to trust our luck.
Even if we have no place to turn to save the mistress,
we will still stay with her no matter what.
Your Lordship!
She is burning up!
Our mistress has always been frail.
The weather aggravated her condition.
She must have caught a cold.
Take this.
During winter, heavy snow often closes
the mountain pass here.
While the roads are still clear,
let's hurry back to the Cooling Terrace.
I thank Your Lordship.
The living quarters on Peak Lingyun
need to be arranged first.
I will go there to prepare the rooms for now.
You can send our mistress back
when she gets better.
Good.
Thank you.
You are responsible for her life now!
I know.
No, you don't.
You are a man.
Men always break women's hearts.
I will do my best to save her,
and on my word, will never hurt her.
I will try my best.
Please trust me.
I will trust you this one time.
Here.
Have you asked Dr. Wen to come?
I sent someone to the palace,
claiming that Your Lordship is sick and
requests only Dr. Wen.
However, the road is slippery when snowy.
Dr. Wen might struggle coming here.
He has to come regardless!
The Cooling Palace lacks medication,
and the mistress has a high fever.
If this goes on,
she might be in danger.
We've tried cold water on her many times,
but My Lady's fever hasn't come down at all.
What can we do?
Quickly.
Jade,
you've been busy all day.
Take a rest. Don't exhaust yourself.
But My Lady...
Other people can take care of her.
You won't be able to care for her
if you wear yourself out.
Ajin,
take Jade to have a rest.
Yes.
Miss Jade, come with me.
I thank Your Lordship.
Continue.
I will watch the mistress.
You may leave too.
Yes.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Your Lordship, are you crazy?
(My wish ran against my will.)
(Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.)
I will do anything to bring her fever down.
[Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.]
Go guard the door and don't breathe a word.
[My unwavering love is gone like flowers
swept away in the wind.]
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.
It's fortunate that...
You finally arrived!
- Peace to Your Lordship.
- Take a look.
It's hard to travel on this snowy night.
Please forgive me my lateness.
I brought some medicine to relieve the fever,
and wrote a prescription.
May I trouble Your Lordship to brew
the medicine here?
Certainly. Go, quickly!
Yes.
Is the mistress getting better?
Fortunately, her fever has come down.
If she kept burning up as your servant said,
we would have had a problem.
Good.
I will go change now,
and check on her later.
Your Lordship, you need to change your clothes!
Your lips are blue.
Don't mention this to anyone!
Your Lordship,
is Dr. Wen here?
He's in there.
You've come at a good time.
Your Lordship, what's wrong?
Nothing. I was walking too fast and
fell into the snow.
Hurry and go inside now.
Your Lordship, why did you come in again?
I will stay here. Your Lordship
can put your mind at ease.
After you finish treating the mistress,
please take a look at me as well.
The past few days...
The past few days I've been having a bad cough.
Your Lordship didn't rest well
and your symptoms persist.
Your Lordship should rest.
Everyone is busy.
I feel bad being the only one resting.
So I came to check.
If I get any worse,
at least we have the doctor nearby.
Miss Jade,
you've been up for most of the night.
How about you go get some rest?
All right.
Dr. Wen,
You should rest soon as well.
Who will look after My Lady if
you were to get sick as well?
How about this?
Tonight...
I'll stay here, too.
Dr. Wen and Jade can sleep here tonight.
So we can take care of each other.
I thank Your Lordship for your consideration.
My Lady, you're awake!
Are you feeling better?
Where am I?
The Cooling Terrace.
You were seriously ill.
So we brought you here to look after you.
I am so happy that I forgot to mention that
Dr. Wen is right over there.
I will ask him to come check on you.
Dr. Wen, My Lady is awake.
Come!
She's much better!
Much better.
Since I'm better now,
we should go back soon.
You are not fully recovered and
need to rest more.
Few people come to the Cooling Terrace.
It's the best place to be.
Staying in the Cooling Terrace might not be good.
If the Cooling Terrace is not good,
what place is better?
Moreover, My Lady is in poor condition.
How would she be able to travel?
Where's Jinxi?
My Lady, I came with you to the Cooling Terrace.
Jinxi went to Peak Lingyun.
So the living quarters are attended to.
Iris, Lotus.
During the past few days when you've been sick,
Jade has been working hard to
take care of you by herself.
Iris and Lotus have been helping
to brew medicine outside for the past few days.
Let's bring them inside to
help Jade take care of you.
His Lordship...
doesn't seem well.
Please attend to him.
His Lordship...
overexerted himself,
and caught a cold,
which caused a fever.
His Lordship needs to sleep under thick covers
to sweat out the cold.
I will also write a prescription for fever.
Then he will be better.
Thank you, Dr. Wen.
Ajin,
come help His Lordship.
It looks like...
It looks like I have to get some sleep.
You need to rest well.
I'll help His Lordship out.
I'm all right here.
Please go take a look at him.
You seem very concerned about him.
Noble Prince Guo has always acted on my behalf.
He is the host here,
who risked his life to save mine.
I'm only...
paying my respects.
You, too, have been working hard,
looking after me for days.
You should go and get some rest as well.
All right.
Rest well.
I will go and check on His Lordship.
His Lordship has always been in good health.
A common cold isn't serious for him.
Just ask His Lordship to rest well.
Thank you, Dr. Wen.
I have had a room prepared for you.
Please take a rest there.
Good.
Ajin!
What is it, Jade?
Is His Lordship all right?
It's not serious. He is all right.
Ajin,
I want to ask you something.
Certainly.
Iris and Lotus...
Did they do something wrong?
They don't dress like ordinary maids,
and dress almost like concubines.
I dare not order them around.
What?
Are they His Lordship's personal maids,
who serve him overnight?
You are being funny.
I'm the only one who serves His Lordship by his side.
They are only ordinary maids.
You may not know that all the servants
here in the Cooling Terrace
were nomads and had no one to rely on.
His Lordship saved them and let them serve here.
They would never have improper thoughts.
You may not know, but I'm sure the mistress does.
His Lordship doesn't want any Lord Consorts or Concubines.
He will marry only one wife.
Ajin,
is His Lordship getting better?
He hasn't recovered from the cold,
and hasn't consumed anything but the medicine.
He is losing weight too.
How did it become so severe?
You may leave now.
I'd like to talk with Ajin in private.
Yes.
His Lordship is a fool,
who likes someone he shouldn't care for
and does senseless things that others wouldn't.
You had a high fever the other day,
and icy towels didn't bring your temperature down.
So His Lordship
lay in the snow with only light clothing on,
and chilled you with his own body.
After several rounds,
your fever finally broke.
After doing this repeatedly,
it was a certainty that he would fall ill.
But...
Don't worry, Mistress.
His Lordship would never act disrespectfully toward you.
You were fully dressed the whole time.
It's not the first time His Lordship has done reckless things.
Ever since he rescued you in the
Palace of Earthly Honor,
I knew that
His Lordship's foolishness would never be cured.
These things...
Why do you tell me?
I don't know why His Lordship makes these futile efforts.
But I know,
His Lordship really did everything he could.
I appreciate His Lordship's thoughts.
His Lordship is sick now.
Mistress, if you have time,
will you go to visit him?
I am a guest in the Cooling Terrace.
It's only proper that I pay His Lordship a visit.
I would go regardless.
You wouldn't understand the circumstances
if I didn't tell you.
There are many fools in the Cooling Terrace.
Some fools are happy for their own reasons
while some fools won't speak up.
His Lordship won't share this with you.
That's why I have to.
Then,
please accompany me to visit His Lordship.
Did Her Venerable Highness come
to visit His Lordship?
Her Venerable Highness is not
allowed to leave the Anqi temple.
So we never sent news about
His Lordship's illness to Her Venerable Highness.
Keep it that way for now.
Otherwise, Her Venerable Highness would be worried.
You are here.
Are you feeling better?
I am able to come here.
Isn't it obvious?
How long have you been here?
Only two hours.
You were sound asleep.
So I didn't want to wake you.
Do you want some water, Yunli?
What did you call me?
Huan'er,
am I dreaming?
Drink some water first.
Your Lordship, His Majesty and
Consort Estime are here.
Why did His Majesty come?
I...
You will run into them if you leave now.
There is a screen.
You can hide behind it.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Without Lord XVII,
I have no one to talk with about poems and paintings.
Peace to...
Since you're sick,
don't be bound by formalities.
Peace to Your Lordship.
Your Majesty and Your Highness
seem to be in a good mood.
But what suddenly brought you here?
The snow finally melted.
It's boring to spend all day in the palace.
I decided to take a short trip.
As we were passing by, I heard of your illness.
Although you still look pale,
your spirit is high.
Longyue heard that her Uncle XVII is sick,
so she specifically came to visit you.
Longyue is here too!
All right. All right. Your Uncle XVII is sick.
Longyue, don't bother him anymore.
She is a clever girl.
She knows you are sick,
and doesn't want you to hold her.
She is as smart as her mother.
Lord XVII,
it's been a while since the last time
you visited the palace.
I'm terribly bored.
I don't even have someone to talk to about poetry and prose.
If she were still here...
When l was young,
When young, I often heard Your Majesty and Empress Première
discussing poetry and prose and writing together.
After that,
only Zhen could hold a conversation with me.
Unfortunately,
she's incorrigible.
Zhen! Zhen!
Do you even know who that is?
You sure know how to repeat words!
I've heard about your Cooling Terrace for a long time.
Now that I've seen it,
it indeed deserves its reputation.
If Your Majesty likes it here,
come visit more often.
It's so difficult to take a trip out of the palace.
Many civil officials are watching me closely.
As good as the Cooling Terrace is,
it needs a lady of the house.
You are not young anymore.
It's time to get married.
It can wait.
If I meet someone I like,
I surely will honor her as the mistress of the Cooling Terrace,
and cherish her for life.
It would be good if you have someone in mind.
If you want,
I can pick some suitable ladies from
distinguished families and you can choose.
Your Majesty must be joking.
It's getting late.
I have to go back and read the memorandums.
You should rest well.
Yes.
There's no need.
It's more important for you to recover.
The road is slippery.
Please be careful, Your Majesty.
He has left.
Even though His Majesty doesn't want to acknowledge it,
You are Longyue's mother after all.
No one can change that.
It's good that Longyue does not know about me.
Having me as her mother...
- Brings shame to her.
- Nonsense!
To have you as her mother
is her greatest pride.
Your Lordship...
Huan’er,
why are you calling me that again?
I lost my manners earlier.
Please forgive me.
Your Lordship, please address me
the same way as before.
Is it because of His Majesty?
His Majesty's visit
woke me up.
I made a mistake earlier,
and was disrespectful to Your Lordship.
His Majesty has never come to the Cooling Terrace.
I don't know why he suddenly came today.
He visited me on a whim.
- But to me and you...
- The world is...
full of the unexpected.
That's not what you said earlier.
We have been troubling Your Lordship for many days.
The snow has melted.
We will take our leave tomorrow,
and go to the living quarters on Peak Lingyun.
For the past few days,
I thank Your Lordship.
Please take your medicine.
My Lady, your health has improved a lot.
I wonder if His Lordship has regained his strength.
He will be better.
Spring is coming.
Everything will be better.
Today is the third day of March -
the Double Third Festival.
And we're bringing gifts for the Consort Dowager.
The Consort Dowager will surely be delighted.
We haven't seen the Consort Dowager in a long time.
It's about time for us to visit.
The weather is nice today.
A beautiful day for you to come here.
I haven't visited Your Venerable Highness in a long time.
Please forgive me.
Peace to Your Venerable Highness.
In a season of such blossoms,
I long to hear the zither.
I've fixed the zither you brought here last time.
You can take the chance to try it out.
I happen to have my flute with me.
We can play together.
I have long heard of your excellent skill with the zither.
I wonder if you would play a song with me.
The original owner of Endless Longing is here.
How could I boast about my skill?
I've never played with Your Lordship.
I'm afraid I won't be able to keep up with Your Lordship's flute.
After the prior emperor passed away,
I stopped playing Endless Longing.
And I haven't heard them being played together since.
Mistress,
please grant this widow's wish and play.
While I'm still alive,
I long to hear the harmonious sound of
Endless Longing and Eternal Promise again.
Since Your Venerable Highness says so,
I'm honored to obey.
What shall we play?
- Endless Longing?
- Endless Longing.
You two are of the same mind.
His Lordship and I only thought of the same song
because the zither's name is Endless Longing.
Even though I'm not well-read,
I do know Li Bai's Endless Longing.
Let's hear it.
Endless longing,
shatters my heart into ruins.
The sun has set, and mist settles on the flowers;
The moon is white as silk on this sleepless night.
I set aside my harp, its inlaid phoenixes entwined
and pick up the zither, its paired strings like coupling love birds.
This song has a meaning that no person can convey;
perhaps it can be carried to Mount Yanran on the Spring winds.
Remembering you, separated by this deep blue sky.
My eyes, once filled with light
now overflow with tears.
If you do not believe my heart aches for you,
come, and seek my eyes in this bright mirror.
After the prior emperor passed away,
it has been a long time since I heard
the duet between Endless Longing and Eternal Promise.
Hearing it again today
reminded me of the time
when I played together with the prior emperor.
Your Venerable Highness is right.
Unlike ordinary zithers and flutes,
playing Endless Longing and Eternal Promise
requires more than skill and experience.
The performers must be kindred spirits
who understand each other,
as if they harbor these emotions themselves.
Otherwise, the sense of longing and promise will be lost.
What Madam Nebular just said,
makes me feel grateful for my blind luck.
It makes sense to say His Lordship and I
are familiar with each other.
But to say that we shared emotion
would expose us to ridicule.
I misspoke out of excitement.
Please forgive me, Mistress.
In the past, it was only a duet between zither and flute.
Mother, with your recitation,
it became ...
perfect, nothing missing.
The music only hints at the emotions.
It's better to speak the lyrics of Endless Longing out loud.
In Your Venerable Highness's voice, we can hear that
the direct expression of love
is better than implicit feelings.
Mistress Zhen,
you truly understand me.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.